Hello and welcome back to part two
of our video on dispersion forces.
So this one we're going to specifically be
looking at dispersion, which is considered
to be the basic force of all compounds.
We're going to try to understand
what the concept of polarizability
is and how this has an effect on
different intermolecular properties.
So where does this all start with?
Well, when we look at all these,
this is the dominant force
for things that are nonpolar.
So things like noble
gases, nonpolar molecules.
But it can be found in all matter, meaning
everything has dispersion, but it's the
strongest or something like nonpolar.
So what is exactly occurring here?
Well, it has to do with the electron
cloud around all these molecules.
So let's say I look at a helium
atom, which is your simplest noble
gas, which has two electrons.
Well, when we are trying to look
at this, well, essentially, if the
electrons try to disperse themselves
from one side to the other.
Where we see that most of the
electrons are all piled up on the
right hand side, this is what makes an
instantaneous dipole, or a temporary one.
Usually this occurs when things collide
with one another, they hit each other,
um, where we have this movement happen.
So whenever we see this, this
is where we have this dipole.
Now, when we're looking at these,
let's say if we go from one to the
other, and let's say one of them
has a dipole, and it collides.
With another atom or another molecule,
which is also nonpolar, it can induce
even more dipoles to occur, where
they can have this weak attraction.
So if you kind of notice, I had to put
in the delta pluses, delta minuses, to
help like really illustrate how they
are actually attracted to one another.
But this is temporary.
It's something that
doesn't last a long time.
The electrons will try to push
each other away because they don't
want to be all bunched up on one
side of the cloud versus another.
They will go back, but it's long enough
for there to be maybe a liquid could form.
Maybe a solid could form for a brief
moment, or if it's cold enough and
they're moving slowly enough for this to
happen where there's not a lot of energy.
For this to actually occur,
so to really show this, where does
this apply to when it comes to it
comes to things is in the boiling
point and melting point of compounds.
So here in what I'm going to show
here is going from temperature.
So we go from cold to hot.
So red being hot, cold being blue.
If we were to put things
like methane, which is CH4.
It's a very simple organic compound,
and if I were to increase the size of
the molecule to, let's say, benzene,
or sorry, not benzene, but hexane,
which is C6H14, we have a six carbon
difference with a lot more atoms.
We can see the temperatures for
the boiling point goes up by almost
200 degrees, and we're only adding
a few more atoms, but there's a
massive difference for nonpolar
molecules the more and more you add.
For every atom, it's going
to make a difference.
So one thing you can ask yourself
is, well, which one has the
stronger energy, like your force?
So the idea here is the stronger
the intermolecular force, the
more it's going to want to hold
it into the liquid phase, right?
So boiling point is all
about it becoming a gas.
So it's like going back
to my video in part one.
One of the things about that was,
well, if you really were to look,
um, essentially through that video
was the one with the stronger
intermolecular force, which was water.
It took a really long time
for that to really break and
to really see that happening.
So in this case, the higher one,
the higher boiling point is the
stronger intermolecular force.
So it's more difficult to separate these.
So the things that we're looking
for is stronger intermolecular
force, which is one.
The second thing is the bigger the
molecule, the harder it is as well.
Those two things that we're looking for at
all these different molecules other ways.
First, look at the size.
Well look at, let's
look at the noble gases.
So if we go from the top, which is helium,
down to neon to argon, tripton to xenon,
one thing that you'll see is that the
molar mass is increasing dramatically.
Meaning, more electrons, more
protons, more neutrons, and also
with this, the temperature of
their boiling point changes too.
Helium is the lowest one, it has 4
Kelvin as its boiling point, it doesn't
take long for it to become a gas.
Whereas, if I were to fill in
the other ones, right, with neon,
argon, krypton, and xenon, you can
see that it goes up, up, up, up,
up, because it's becoming heavier.
Those electrons are harder,
essentially, it's a more of an
attraction, because there's more
of them on one side versus another.
The bigger, the more attraction,
when we are trying to look at them.
The more molar mass, the more attraction.
So, now this is what we refer to as
polarizability, is the key word here.
So more mass is a larger
polarizability, which means that it's
going to have a stronger dispersion
force between the molecules.
This is important for general chemistry,
introductory organic chemistry, to
understand how we can predict how
chemicals will behave when they're
a solid, a liquid, or a gas, um,
with all these different substances.
Okay, so, and you can really see how we
have heaviest to lightest, looking at
all these little individual components.
Now, when we're trying to, how
can I exactly explain what this
means, how does this come about?
Well, this whole idea of instantaneous
dipole, well, like I mentioned before,
it has to do with the electrons, right?
So I listed their electron configuration
here, and their total electron count.
And you can see with helium, right,
that was the simplest one, two
electrons, it had like four kelvin.
Where xenon has 54 electrons and
went to 165 kelvin, you know,
160K difference, that's a lot,
that's a big temperature shift.
So how, why, how can we explain this?
Well, you have to try to think of
what is the probability of all of them
being shifted to one side or the other?
How long will they stay
attracted to each other for?
So one way to think of in a really, really
simplistic model is let's say I take an
electron and I treat it like a coin flip,
meaning it can either be on the left
side or the right side and that's it.
So if I were to try to do the
probability of that, well, there's a
50 percent chance it can 50 percent
chance it's going to go on the right.
So if you need both of the electrons for
helium to go on one side, well, you have,
you know, about a 50, 50 chance a little
bit for them to go on the same side and
you can try to do this for all these
different electrons to see, okay, well.
Where are they going to be?
So if I were to say to make them an even
distribution, so where I have one electron
on the left for helium, one electron on
the right, it's like about a 50 50 chance.
Now to evenly distribute all the other
Electrons for, let's say, um, for neon
from argon to krypton to xenon, it
becomes increasingly more difficult to
get them to be even between the two sides.
So in the, what does that mean is
that there's always going to be a
little bit of an instantaneous dipole
for bigger molecules because it's
impossible almost to have it perfect.
So you can see xenon, it's like a
10 percent chance for it to be even,
meaning most of the time it's having.
attraction between other xenon.
So, and that's one of the reasons why
we are actually seeing that difference.
So, what is the pattern here in the end?
Well, one thing is, the more
electrons, or the heavier it gets,
the probability of unevenness goes up.
So we will always have this
instantaneous dipole for really, really
big molecules because it's likely
that they're not going to be even.
So this is what we mean by polarizability.
It allows us to be able to predict
exactly what forces we are going to see.
So the bigger it is.
The higher the melting point, the higher
the boiling point, which is really,
really important when we're trying to
understand how the chemistry works, right?
So that is one thing.
So bigger, stronger dispersion
is one of the things that we are
trying to get out of this video.
All right, let's take a
look at some other ones.
So going back to the example from before,
right, where I mentioned methane and
then hexane, which was six carbons.
Here I have essentially one carbon,
two carbons, three, four, five.
And we can see the temperatures
are increasing as well.
So if we were to put all those on a chart,
the bigger it gets, the higher it goes.
So what can you try to say about that?
Well, from heaviest to lightest, the
heaviest one has the strongest force
of attraction to other molecules
of the same type, making them a
lot more difficult to separate.
So larger molecules have higher
polarizability, which makes them
have essentially a stronger force of
attraction and more likely to be a liquid
or even a solid the bigger it gets.
One way to think of it too when it comes
to organic molecules like these, methane,
propane and butane are all gases, right?
Propane you find in stoves or
butane you might find in a lighter.
It's generally a gas and starts to
become a liquid as you go through
depending on how much pressure it has.
Whereas, let's say octane,
which is what you fill your
car with, is a liquid, right?
You know, we call it gasoline in the US.
It's a liquid.
Um, and the farther and farther you go
is when you eventually start becoming
a solid, when you add enough of these
carbons to the molecule, you get more and
more attracted to each other as you go.
So just to kind of practice this concept,
well, predict which one would have
the strongest intermolecular force.
So I have two molecules here, I
have hydrogen and oxygen, both of
them are linear, meaning they're
going to be non polar diatomics.
Every diatomic is non polar,
which is one of the most
important things to keep in mind.
Which one is more?
Well, hydrogen, right, is One
of your smallest elements.
So when we're trying to look at
it, right, the first thing you
want to do is, are they not polar?
As I just said, they are.
The next thing we're going to look at
is, well, let's see if we can figure
out the sizes of each one of them.
Well, if we want to look at the
sizes, well, hydrogen looks like
the Lewis structure on the left.
Oxygen looks like the one on the right.
They look about identical when
it comes to electronegativity.
So when we look at both of
them, right, oxygen has a molar
mass of 32 grams per mole.
Hydrogen has a molar mass of two, so it's
two electrons versus about 16 electrons.
That's a huge difference between the
two, meaning that hydrogen, the odds of
the electrons being even is pretty high,
where something like oxygen are such a
big volume here, there's such a large area
for the polarizability to occur that's
gonna lead to a stronger dispersion force.
So oxygen is going to be
a lot higher as a result.
Okay, so you're looking at how bigger,
which one's bigger, is the sum of this.
Let's look at this next one.
So CF4 and CBr4.
Well, fluorine is, so it's pretty much
carbon, carbon, they're the same size.
So fluorine versus bromine.
Fluorine is in the top right
corner of your periodic table.
Bromine is a little bit lower.
So which one would have the
stronger dispersion force?
These are both non polar, right, because
they both are tetrahedral geometries.
The heavier of the two is
going to be bromine, right?
So CBr4 is going to have a
much larger volume to it.
It's going to be more electrons,
more dispersion that's going to be
occurring, a higher polarizability.
So out of these two, the one that's
going to be stronger is going to be CBr4.
It's going to be the key here.
Now, to sum up everything we talked about.
How do we keep dispersion correct?
All molecules do this force.
It's considered to be a universal
attractive force between all of them.
So this is something that they all
can do as their, this temporary
dipoles just because electrons are
not even between the molecules.
However, it's essentially the
most prominent force for, for
anything that's non polar.
So whenever we're looking at these, how
do we figure out which one's bigger?
Well, it's generally based on the
number of electrons, which means more
valence shells, the larger it is.
So we want to look at which one's
the biggest of all, what's the
heaviest in terms of molar mass.
So look at your molar mass,
figure out what's the heaviest.
And that is going to be your answer.
So now keep in mind though, when you
have, let's say, stronger intermolecular
forces, they will override dispersion.
So if you have something that's
polar, that automatically is going
to be strong, stronger interaction.
Um, so we always look at
intermolecular force first,
then we look at size afterwards.
Um, and that's what we're looking
at for intermolecular forces.
I hope this video helped you trying to
understand part two of our video here.
So thank you so much for watching
and please stick around for
more on intermolecular forces.